<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: bash | The {pnk}f(eli)x Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.pnkfx.org/blog/categories/bash/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.pnkfx.org/"/>
  <updated>2022-05-12T02:01:07-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.pnkfx.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Felix S. Klock II]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Better command completion in bash on OS X]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.pnkfx.org/blog/2013/04/12/better-command-completion-in-bash-aka-resolving-zsh-envy/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-12T07:57:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.pnkfx.org/blog/2013/04/12/better-command-completion-in-bash-aka-resolving-zsh-envy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>(This post started as a personal e-mail to Niko, and then I figured it
was blog worthy.)</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s plenty of problems when working atop &ldquo;OS X&rdquo;;
but no need to be jealous of Shu&rsquo;s zsh setup
(at least not for its tab-completion on git stuff),
at least not if you are already using Homebrew.
Just install
<a href="http://blog.jeffterrace.com/2012/09/bash-completion-for-mac-os-x.html">brew&rsquo;s bash completion package</a>!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Executive summary:</p>

<pre><code class="bash">% brew install bash-completion

% echo &gt;&gt; ~/.bash_profile &lt;&lt;END
  if [ -f $(brew --prefix)/etc/bash_completion ]; then
    . $(brew --prefix)/etc/bash_completion
  fi
END
</code></pre>

<p>And voilà!</p>

<p>See also potentially related topics from <a href="http://superuser.com/questions/288438/bash-completion-for-commands-in-mac-os">super user</a>, <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/14970728/homebrews-git-not-using-completion">stack overflow</a>, <a href="http://milkbox.net/note/brace-completion-in-snow-leopard-upgrading-bash/">milkbox blog</a>.</p>

<hr />

<p>Note also that I did burn myself by trying to get too smart: In
particular, after reading <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/14970728/homebrews-git-not-using-completion">stack overflow</a>, I over-eagerly
attempted to address a purported problem by installing the homebrew
newer git instead of the default (older) built-in git installed by
Apple.</p>

<p>This was a little more painful than I expected, because there were a
bunch of git-related commands already in my <code>/usr/local/bin</code>, probably
I had likely already copied git to there once before by hand, and so
brew kept aborting the installation because it did not want to
overwrite the binaries that it was not already managing.  I think brew
was aborting the install in a sound transactional manner, but I am not
100% sure of that, because at least one point the command completion
stopped working and at that point I just</p>

<ol>
<li>gave up on understanding where everything came from,</li>
<li>moved the non-brew git-related material
in <code>/usr/local/bin/</code> out of the way, and</li>
<li>redid the <code>brew install git</code></li>
</ol>


<hr />

<p>Anyway, I should also give a shout-out to Axel Hecht; his post
on Mozilla&rsquo;s Yammer instance is what got me to the point of even
attempting to install this piece of marvelousness.</p>

<p>(Also, further posts on yammer are lightly pushing for readers to consider
zsh as an alternative to bash.  I do not think I am ready to switch to zsh,
but I can at least link to the <a href="http://friedcpu.wordpress.com/2007/07/24/zsh-the-last-shell-youll-ever-need/">blog post arguing for zsh</a>.)</p>

<hr />

<p>Update (written 2013 april 16): Now that I have decent command/context
sensitive completion in bash in my terminal, of <em>course</em> I
want to have it in my Emacs <code>M-x shell</code> as well.  At first I
was dismayed that I did not just get that &ldquo;out of the box&rdquo;;
then I was happy after some googling to discover:
<a href="https://github.com/szermatt/emacs-bash-completion">bash-completion.el</a>, which forwards the completion
requests onto a separate bash process, so that one inherits
the same completions that bash provides in the terminal,
with no Emacs hacking.</p>

<p>Well, at least, not very much Emacs hacking.</p>

<p>It turns out that I had to do a little bit of Emacs hacking
in order to get the setup working, at least for my idiosyncratic
bash setup.  In particular, it seems like the Elisp code
for bash-complete.el assumes that one is setting one&rsquo;s
prompt via the <code>PS1</code> environment variable, while mine is often
set via the <code>PROMPT_COMMAND</code> environment variable.
After determining what is going on, it is easy enough to fix this (and
the corresponding solution has even been filed as a <a href="https://github.com/szermatt/emacs-bash-completion/pull/2">pull request in
the github repo</a>).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
