<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: git | The {pnk}f(eli)x Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.pnkfx.org/blog/categories/git/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.pnkfx.org/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-12T14:18:46+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.pnkfx.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Felix S. Klock II]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Better command completion in bash on OS X]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.pnkfx.org/blog/2013/04/12/better-command-completion-in-bash-aka-resolving-zsh-envy/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-12T07:57:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.pnkfx.org/blog/2013/04/12/better-command-completion-in-bash-aka-resolving-zsh-envy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>(This post started as a personal e-mail to Niko, and then I figured it
was blog worthy.)</p>

<p>There&#39;s plenty of problems when working atop &quot;OS X&quot;;
but no need to be jealous of Shu&#39;s zsh setup
(at least not for its tab-completion on git stuff),
at least not if you are already using Homebrew.
Just install
<a href="http://blog.jeffterrace.com/2012/09/bash-completion-for-mac-os-x.html">brew&#39;s bash completion package</a>!</p>

<p>Executive summary: </p>
<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="bash">% brew install bash-completion

% <span class="nb">echo</span> &gt;&gt; ~/.bash_profile <span class="s">&lt;&lt;END</span>
<span class="s">  if [ -f $(brew --prefix)/etc/bash_completion ]; then</span>
<span class="s">    . $(brew --prefix)/etc/bash_completion</span>
<span class="s">  fi</span>
<span class="s">END</span>
</code></pre></div>
<p>And voilà!</p>

<p>See also potentially related topics from <a href="http://superuser.com/questions/288438/bash-completion-for-commands-in-mac-os">super user</a>, <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/14970728/homebrews-git-not-using-completion">stack overflow</a>, <a href="http://milkbox.net/note/brace-completion-in-snow-leopard-upgrading-bash/">milkbox blog</a>.</p>

<hr>

<p>Note also that I did burn myself by trying to get too smart: In
particular, after reading <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/14970728/homebrews-git-not-using-completion">stack overflow</a>, I over-eagerly
attempted to address a purported problem by installing the homebrew
newer git instead of the default (older) built-in git installed by
Apple.</p>

<p>This was a little more painful than I expected, because there were a
bunch of git-related commands already in my <code>/usr/local/bin</code>, probably
I had likely already copied git to there once before by hand, and so
brew kept aborting the installation because it did not want to
overwrite the binaries that it was not already managing.  I think brew
was aborting the install in a sound transactional manner, but I am not
100% sure of that, because at least one point the command completion
stopped working and at that point I just</p>

<ol>
<li>gave up on understanding where everything came from,</li>
<li>moved the non-brew git-related material
in <code>/usr/local/bin/</code> out of the way, and</li>
<li>redid the <code>brew install git</code></li>
</ol>

<hr>

<p>Anyway, I should also give a shout-out to Axel Hecht; his post
on Mozilla&#39;s Yammer instance is what got me to the point of even
attempting to install this piece of marvelousness.</p>

<p>(Also, further posts on yammer are lightly pushing for readers to consider
zsh as an alternative to bash.  I do not think I am ready to switch to zsh,
but I can at least link to the <a href="http://friedcpu.wordpress.com/2007/07/24/zsh-the-last-shell-youll-ever-need/">blog post arguing for zsh</a>.)</p>

<hr>

<p>Update (written 2013 april 16): Now that I have decent command/context
sensitive completion in bash in my terminal, of <em>course</em> I
want to have it in my Emacs <code>M-x shell</code> as well.  At first I
was dismayed that I did not just get that &quot;out of the box&quot;;
then I was happy after some googling to discover:
<a href="https://github.com/szermatt/emacs-bash-completion">bash-completion.el</a>, which forwards the completion
requests onto a separate bash process, so that one inherits
the same completions that bash provides in the terminal,
with no Emacs hacking.</p>

<p>Well, at least, not very much Emacs hacking.</p>

<p>It turns out that I had to do a little bit of Emacs hacking
in order to get the setup working, at least for my idiosyncratic
bash setup.  In particular, it seems like the Elisp code
for bash-complete.el assumes that one is setting one&#39;s
prompt via the <code>PS1</code> environment variable, while mine is often
set via the <code>PROMPT_COMMAND</code> environment variable.
After determining what is going on, it is easy enough to fix this (and
the corresponding solution has even been filed as a <a href="https://github.com/szermatt/emacs-bash-completion/pull/2">pull request in
the github repo</a>).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Resurrected (Hello Again World)]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.pnkfx.org/blog/2013/01/08/resurrected-hello-again-world/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-08T00:55:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.pnkfx.org/blog/2013/01/08/resurrected-hello-again-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="toc_0">It&#39;s Clobbering Time</h2>

<p>Remember that thing I said back <a href="/blog/2012/12/31/hello-world">at the end of 2012</a>?
That thing?
That thing about the important detail that:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>the <code>_deploy/</code> subdirectory is itself a clone of the targeted
github repository, with the <code>gh-pages</code> branch checked out.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It turns out this is really important detail.</p>

<p>Here&#39;s why: For my first blogging act of the new year, I inadvertently destroyed
my own blog.</p>

<p>I attempted to write a post from a computer other than the one out of
which I had already worked all the octopress-compatibility kinks.
In the hustle of dealing with <code>rbenv</code> and various other ruby-oriented
dependencies, I forgot about the detail above.</p>

<p>And then when I ran <code>rake deploy</code>, I clobbered the live blog.</p>

<p>I may have been recovering from, or incapacitated by, New Years
revelry at the time, it is not clear to me at the current moment.  I
believe I identified the disaster right after it happened, but immediately
decided I did not have the time then to diagnose it, fix it,
or even to attempt to rollback the
state and repush to github.  I vaguely remember considering that last option
and deciding that even that was out of the question.  (I think a pending
trip to a Karaoke bar may have been involved in the decision-making
process here.)</p>

<p>So, tonight I diagnosed and fixed the problem.</p>

<p>At first I was just going to let the matter lie undocumented, and
pretend like it never happened.</p>

<p>But I realized that I may well again make the same mistake in the future,
and that it behooved me to at least document the issue in my commit
log for <a href="https://github.com/pnkfelix/pnkfx-blog/commits/blog.pnkfx.org">the blog source</a>.</p>

<p>And after writing that commit log entry and pushing it, I decided that
this story was in fact blog worthy; after all, what is the point of
a blog if not to freely broadcast your mistakes?  :)</p>

<p>So, directly from <a href="https://github.com/pnkfelix/pnkfx-blog/commit/f277b041de33a8e0eac02c6aecb3909231725db7">my commit message</a>, here is the description of how
I clobbered my own blog:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>The easy way to sum it up is: The model
employed by octopress when deploying to github is this: Your _deploy/
subdirectory must contain a checkout of the target repo, the one with
the gh-pages branch, and you must have that _deploy/ subdirectory
checked out and ready to go before running &#39;rake deploy&#39;.</p>

<p>If you do not have a _deploy/ subdirectory at all and you let &#39;rake
deploy&#39; create it for you but you also let &#39;rake deploy&#39; attempt to
push to github, and you are also managing the source itself on github,
you will enter a world of pain where the rake invocation will push
<em>this</em> root directory, presumably in the master branch (or in my case,
blog.pnkfx.org branch) to the target repo in the gh-pages/ branch.
Which will bust things terribly, especially if that causes the CNAME
file to get deleted from the gh-pages/ branch of the target repo.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="toc_1">A note on self-reference</h2>

<p>Also, a quick half shout-out, or maybe corrective note, to
<a href="http://www.seamusbradley.net/blog/blog/2012/04/24/how-to-link-to-your-own-blog-posts-in-octopress/">seamusbradley</a> for pointing out some details about linking back to
one&#39;s own blog posts.</p>

<p>It is only a half shout-out because Seamus&#39;s note is only useful, I
think, if you have, like him, a customized setting for the <code>root:</code> in
your <code>_config.yml</code>.  That, or Seamus has confused himself and changed
his <code>root</code> setting in order to accommodate other url&#39;s that he
observed, but those urls are in fact actually generated by settings
for properties other than <code>root</code>.</p>

<p>Here&#39;s the concrete details: I read (misread?) Seamus&#39;s post at first
as saying that a customized setting of <code>root</code> to <code>/blog</code> is a
prerequisite for linking to your own posts.  It seems to me that the
relevant detail is what the <em>permalink</em> setting is, not the root.
(But then again, I have not played with changing my root setting,
apart from finding that when I did try changing it to <code>/blog</code> as
Seamus suggested, it seems like doing so broke <code>rake preview</code>.)</p>

<p>In my case, the <code>root</code> and <code>permalink</code> for my <code>_config.yml</code>
are set as follows:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="text">root: /
permalink: /blog/:year/:month/:day/:title/
</code></pre></div>
<p>and I format links to my own posts, such as the one you are reading,
like so:
<a href="/blog/2013/01/08/resurrected-hello-again-world"><code>/blog/2013/01/08/resurrected-hello-again-world</code></a>
as you can see from looking at the source for the line above,</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="text">[`/blog/2013/01/08/resurrected-hello-again-world`](/blog/2013/01/08/resurrected-hello-again-world)
</code></pre></div>
<p>A bit of quoted self-reference is a good place to stop for the night.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
